This video will prove the correctness of
our greedy algorithm for clustering.
We'll show that it maximizes the spacing
over all possible K clusterings.
You might have hoped that we could deduce
the correctness of this greedy algorithm
for clustering immediately from our
correctness proofs for various greedy
minimum spanning tree algorithms.
Unfortunately that doesn't seem to be the
case.
In the minimum cost spanning tree
problem, we're focusing on minimizing the
sum of the edge cost.
Here we're looking at different
objective, maximizing the spacings.
We do need to do a proof from scratch.
That's said, you know, the arguments
we'll use should look familiar to you not
just from the sort of exchange type
arguments when we prove the cut property,
but also it might remind you even more,
going back further, to our greedy
algorithms for scheduling.
So let's now set up the notation for the
proof.
As usual, we're going to look at the
output of r algorithm.
It achieves some objective function
value, some spacing.
We're going to look at an arbitrary
competitor.
Some other proposed scheduling.
We're going to show that we're at least
as good,
our spacing is, at least, as large.
So specifically, we'll denote the
clusters in the output of r algorithm by
C1 up to CK.
Our clustering has some spacing, some
distance between the near, closest pair
of separated points.
Call it capital S.
We're going to denote our competitor,
some alternative K clustering by C-Hat
one of the C-Hat K, what is it that we're
tryin to show?
We want to show that this arbitrary other
clustering has spacing no larger than
R's, if we can show that, then because
this clustering was arbitrary it means
the greedy clustering has spacing as
large as any other, so it's maximizing
the spacing, that's what we want to
proof.
But differently we want to exhibit a pair
of points separated by this cluster and C
one-half to C1K, such that the distance
between those separated points is S or
smaller.
So, let me just quickly depose of a
trivial case.
If the C hats are the same as the C's,
possibly up to a renaming, then of course
exactly the same pairs of points are
separated into each of the clustering, so
that the spacing is exactly the same.
So that's not a case we have to worry
about.
The interesting case, then, is when the c
hats differ fundamentally from the cs,
when they're not merely a permutation of
the clusters in the greedy clustering.
And the maneuver we're going to do here
is similar in spirit to what we did in
our scheduling correctness proof.
Way back in our scheduling correctness
proof, we argued that any schedule that
differs from the greedy one, suffers
from, in some sense, a local flaw.
We identified an adjacent pair of jobs
that was, in some sense, out of order
with respect to the greedy ordering.
The analog here is, we're going to argue
that, for any clustering which is not
merely a permutation of the greedy
clustering.
There has to be a pair of points which is
classified differently in the c hats
relative to the c's.
By differently, I mean they're clustered
together in the greedy clustering.
These points, p and q, belong to the same
cluster, c sub i.
Yet, in this alternative clustering,
which is not just the permutation of the
greedy clustering.
They're placed in different clusters.
One, maybe p and c hat i,
and q and some other c hat j.
So I want to now split the proof into an
easy case and a tricky case.
To explain why the easy case is easy
lets, lets observe a property that this
greedy clustering algorithm has.
Now the algorithm's philosophy is that
the squeaky wheel should get the grease.
That is, the separated pair of points
that are closest to each other are the
ones that should get merged.
So for this reason, because it's always
the closest separated pair that get
merged, if you look at the sequence of
point pairs that get merged together,
that determine the spacing in each
subsequent iteration, the distances
between these sort of worst separated
points is only going up over time.
At the beginning of the algorithm,
the closest pair of points in the entire
point set are the ones that get directly
merged.
Then those are out of the picture,
and now that some further away pair of
points are separated, it determines the
spacing,
then they get merged.
Once they've been coalesced, then there
is still some further away pair of
points, which is now the smallest
separated.
They get merged, and so on.
So if you look at the sequence of
distances between the pairs of points
that are directly merged by the greedy
algorithm, that is only going up over
time.
And this sequence culminates with the
final spacing S of the greedy algorithm.
At some sense, the spacing of the output
of the greedy algorithm is the distance
between the point period that would get
merged if we ran the greedy algorithm one
more in moderation but unfortunately
we're not allowed to do that.
Okay?
So the point is, for every pair of points
directly merged by the greedy algorithm,
they're always a distance at most S away
from each other.
So the easy case, then, is when this pair
of points, pq,
which, on the one hand, lie in a common
greedy structure,
but on the other hand, in different
clusters with c hats.
If they were, at some point, not merely
in the same cluster, but actually
directly merged by the greedy algorithm.
If, at some iteration, they determined
the spacing, and were picked by the
greedy algorithm to have their, clusters
merged.
Then we just argued that the distance
between p and q is no more than the space
in capital s of the greedy clustering.
And since p and q lie in different
clusters of the c hats.
It's separated by the C hats and
therefore they upper bound the spacing of
the C hats.
Maybe there's some even closer separated
pair by the C hats.
But the very least P and Q are separated
so they upper bound the spacing of the C
hat clustering.
So that's what we wanted to prove.
We wanted to show that this alternative
spacing didn't have better spacing than
our greedy spacing.
It had to be at most as big.
It had to be at most capital S.
So in this easy case, when P and Q are
directly merged by the greedy algorithm,
we're done.
So the tricky case is when P and Q are
only indirectly merged, and you may be
wondering at the moment, what does that
mean?
How did two people wind up in the same
cluster if they weren't, at some point,
directly merged?
So let's draw a picture and see how that
can happen.
So the issue is that two points P and Q
might wind up in a common greeting
cluster,
not because the greedy algorithm ever
explicitly considered that point pair,
but rather because of a path or cascade
of direct mergers of other point pairs.
Imagine, for example, that at some
iteration of the greedy algorithm the
point P was considered explicitly along
with the point A1, where here A1 is meant
to be different than Q.
So that's a direct merger, and P and A1
wind up in the same cluster. Their
clusters are merged.
Maybe the same thing happened to the
point Q at some point A sub L which is
different than P.
Sooner or later maybe, you know, at some
other time, some totally unrelated pair
of points A2 and A3 are directly merged
and then at some point A1 and A2 are
considered by the greedy algorithm.
Algorithm, because the other closest pair
of separated points, and, they get
merged.
And so on.
So the edges in this picture are meant to
indicate direct mergers, pairs of points
that are explicitly fused because they
determine the spacing of some point of
the greedy iteration.
But at the end of the day the greedy
clustering is going to have the results
of all of these mergings.
So in case you're feeling confused, let
me just point out that we really saw this
exact same exact thing going on when we
were talking about minimum spanning trees
in Kruskal's rhythm.
So, at an intermediate point in Kruskal's
rhythm, after it's added some edges, but
before it's constructed a spanning tree.
As we discussed, the intermediate state
is a bunch of different connected
components.
And there are vertices that Have an edge
chosen between them.
They, of course, are going to be in the
same kinetic component.
But then again, a kenetic component could
have long paths in it.
So you could have vertices that are in
the same kinetic component in an
intermediate state of Kruskal's
Algorithm, despite the fact that we've
haven't chosen an edge directly between
them.
There's rather, a path of chosen edges
between them.
It's exactly the same thing going on
here.
Now, what we have going for us is that,
if a pair of points, as discussed, was
directly merged, we know they're close.
The distance between them is, at most,
this spacing, capital S.
We really don't know anything, frankly,
about the distance between pairs of
vertices that were not directly merged.
They just, sort of, accidentally wound up
in a common cluster.
But this turns out to be good enough.
This is actually sufficient to argue that
this competitor clustering with the c-hat
has spacing no more than s?
No better than ours.
Let's see why.
So given that P and Q are in a common
greedy cluster it must mean there was a
path of direct mergers that forced them
to be in the same cluster.
So let's let the intermediate points
involved in that path denoted A1 of two
AL.
So here's the part of the proof where we
basically reduce the tricky case to the
easy case.
So we've got this pair of points, PQ.
Now, remember, not, not only are they in
a common greedy cluster.
But they're in different clusters in our
competitor in the c hats.
So the point p is in some cluster.
Call it c hat i.
And Q is in something else.
In particular, it's not in c hat i.
Now, imagine you go on a hike.
You start at the point p, and you hike
along this path.
You traverse these direct mergers toward
q.
Now, you're starting inside c hat I, and
you end up outside.
So at some point on your hike, you will
traverse the boundary.
You will, for the first time, escape from
c hat I, and wind up in some other
cluster.
So that has to happen.
And let's call ai and ai+1 the
consecutive pair of points at which you
go from inside this cluster to outside
this cluster.
And now we're back in the easy case.
Now we're dealing with a separated pair
that would directly merge by the greedy
algorithm.
Remember that we set up this path to be a
path of direct mergers so in particular,
AJ and AJ + one were direct mergers,
therefore their distance is at most S.
And again, by virtue of being direct
mergers, their distance is at most the
spacing of the greedy clustering and yet
as a separated point by the C hats.
It's also an upper bound on the spacing
of the C hats.
This means the spacing S of our greedy
clustering is as good as the competitor.
Is the competitor was arbitrary or
optimal.
That completes the proof.